You all know this story.
جميعكم تعرفون هذه القصة
In the summer of 1950,
في صيف عام 1950
Enrico Fermi, the Italian-American physicist
توجه الفيزيائي الايطالي اميركي انريكو فيرمي
and atomic-pile builder,
وباني البطارية الذرية
went to lunch at Los Alamos National Laboratory
للغداء في مخبر لوس الموس الوطني
and joined some colleagues there, and asked them a question:
هناك اجتمع ببعض الزملاء حيث سألهم
"Where is everybody?"
اين الجميع ؟
This confused his colleagues, obviously,
هنا ارتبك زملاؤه
because they were sitting right there with him.
فمن الواضح بأنهم يجلسون أمامه
And then he had to clarify that he wasn't talking about them.
ليوضح لهم فيما بعد بأنه لم يكن يقصدهم بسؤاله
He was talking about the space aliens.
هو يتحدث عن الرجال الفضائيين
You see, this was only a few years after
حدث هذا بعد أعوام قليلة
the supposed flying saucer crash
مما يفترض أن يكون تحطم طبق طائر
at Roswell, New Mexico.
في راسول, نيو مكسيكو
And even though that turned out to be nothing,
وعلى الرغم من ذلك تحول هذا الحدث الى اللاشيء
nothing at all --
لاشئ بالمرة
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
merely a downed weather balloon
سقوط منطاد جوي لااكثر
piloted by small hairless men
يقوده رجل اصلع
with slits for mouths ...
يشق الجو كي يأكل
Still, America had gone saucer-mad,
الى الان لازال في أمريكا الكثير من مجانين الاطباق الفضائية
even famous scientists
حتى اشهر العلماء
who were eating lunch.
الذي كان يتناول الغداء
Fermi's reasoning, if I may paraphrase badly,
من وجهة نظر فيرمي , قد أعيد صياغتها بشكل سييء,
is that the universe is so vast
أن الكون واسع جدا
that it stands to reason,
ولهذا السبب
there should be other intelligent life out there.
يجب أن يكون هناك حياة ذكية في مكان ما فيه
And the universe is so old
وبأن الكون قديم جدا أيضا
that unless we were the very first civilization ever to evolve,
الا اذا كنا أولى الحضارات التي ظهرت على وجه الارض
we should have some evidence of their existence by now.
في هذه الحال يجب علينا جمع الادلة على وجودهم من الان
And yet, to the best of our knowledge, we are alone.
وعلى الرغم من ذلك فمن الافضل لمعرفتنا أن نكون الوحيدين
"Where is everybody?" asked Fermi,
سأل فيرمي أين الجميع ؟
and his colleagues had no answer.
وزملاؤه لم يملكوا اجابة
Fermi then went on with the same blunt logic
اكمل فيرمي بذات المنطق الاعوج
to disprove fairies,
لينكر الجنيات
Sasquatch, God,
الغولة,الاله
the possibility of love --
امكانية الحب
and thereafter, as you know,
بعد ذلك كما تعلمون
Enrico Fermi ate alone.
أكمل انريكو فيرمي طعامه لوحده
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now,
الان,
I am not a scientist.
انا لست بعالم
I have never built an atomic pile.
ولم ابني يوما بطارية ذرية
Although, I might argue that, technically,
لكني استطيع ان اجادل في ذلك , تقنيا
every pile is atomic.
كل بطارية من البطاريات هي ذرية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
However, with respect, I might point out two possibilities
مع كل الاحترام طبعا , ولكني أريد أن اثير احتمالين
that Enrico Fermi perhaps did not consider.
ربما لم يضعهما انريكو فيرمي في حسبانه
One is that the aliens might be
أولهما أنه ربما كان الفضائيون
very far away.
بعيدون جدا
Perhaps, I dare say,
ربماأستطيع القول
even on other planets.
أنهم على كوكب آخر تماما
The other possibility --
الاحتمال الاخر
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
is, perhaps, Enrico Fermi himself
انه ربما كان انريكو فيرمي نفسه
was an alien.
مخلوق فضائي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Think about it.
فكروا فيها
Isn't it a little convenient
أوليست مقنعة ولو قليلا ؟
that in the midst of the World War, out of nowhere,
كان هذا الحدث في منتصف الحرب العالمية في مكان ما
suddenly an Italian scientist showed up
ليتقدم أحد العلماء الايطاليين ويعطي للعالم
with an amazing new technology
تكنولوجيا مذهلة جديدة كليا
that would transform everything in the world
قادرة على تحويل كل شيء في العالم
and darken the history of the human species forever after?
وتسويد كل ماسبقه من تاريخنا الانساني
And isn't it a little strange
لكن اليس غريبا
that he required no payment for this?
انه لم يطالب بأي مقابل
That he asked for only one thing --
سوى شيء واحد فقط
a gift of two healthy sperm whales?
هدية عبارة عن حوتان عنبر صحيان
That's -- that's not true.
هذا -- غير صحيح طبعا
But it is strange.
لكنه غريب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And if Enrico Fermi were indeed a space alien,
اذا كان انريكو فيرمي مخلوق فضائي حقا
wouldn't he be the first to have tried to convince
ألن يكون من الاحرى به اقناع
his fellow scientists
رفاقه العلماء
that the space aliens are not already here?
بأن المخلوقات الفضائية غير موجودة
For it is given in certain UFO-ology
بدلا من التأكيد على وجود اليوفو
or UFOlogy circles,
او دائرة معارف اليوفو
that the aliens are already here and have been for millennia;
هذا أن المخلوقات الفضائية موجودة هنا منذ الاف السنين
that they have walked among us in disguise,
ذلك أنهم يعيشون بيننا متنكرين
observing us, guiding our evolution
يراقبوننا , يوجهون حضارتنا
from ape to man --
من القرد الى الانسان
if you believe in that sort of thing --
اذا افترضنا انكم ممن يصدق مثل تلك الاشياء
and, occasionally, kidnapping us in their flying saucers
وبين الفينة والاخرى يختطفوننا بصحونهم الطائرة
and taking us away to have sex with us in pyramids.
ليمارسوا الجنس معنا في الاهرامات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a difficult theory to discount,
من الصعب حسم مثل هكذا أفكار
I think you'll agree.
أعتقد بأنكم ستوافقونني الرأي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
For even in my own life,
حتى في حياتي
there are memories I have
هناك ذكريات تخللت حياتي
that are difficult to explain --
من الصعب شرحها
happenings that are so odd and unaccountably weird,
حدثت بشكل غريب , مجهول كليا
that it is difficult to imagine
من الصعب حتى تصورها
they were not the result
لم تحدث نتيحة
of prolonged and frequent contact with aliens throughout my life.
لاتصالات دورية مطولة بيني وبين المخلوقات الفضائية
For how else will you explain
والا فكيف لكم أن تفسروا
the amazing and absolutely true
تلك اللقاءات الحقيقة والمذهلة كليا
close encounters that I had
التي صادفتها
and will describe to you now?
والتي سأقوم بشرحها الان
Encounter one: Ocean City, New Jersey, 1980.
اللقاء الاول : كورنيش المحيط , نيوجرسي . 1980
This was the summer when the special edition of
كان هذا في الصيف عندما صدرت الطبعة الخاصة من
"Close Encounters of the Third Kind" was released.
" لقاءات قريبة من النوع الثالث "
And I went on vacation with my parents to the Jersey shore.
توجهت مع والديّ لقضاء الاجازةعلى شاطئ جيرسي
Within 12 hours, I was horribly sunburned,
وخلال 12 ساعة كنت مصاب بحروق شمسية مخيفة
just like Richard Dreyfuss in the movie.
كريتشارد دريفز في الفيلم
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
And so I spent the rest of the vacation
لذا أكملت بقية العطلة
largely sitting outside our little rental house at night,
بالبقاء خارج منزلنا المستأجر في المساء
the sidewalk still warm from the sun,
كان الرصيف مازال دافئا من الشمس
watching the skies for UFOs.
أراقب السماء من أجل اليوفو
What did I see? Stars, satellites,
ماذا رأيت ؟ نجوم , أقمار الصناعية
blinking airplanes -- typical sky junk.
طائرات , سماء غير مرغوبة بالمرة
Occasionally, kids would come and
بين الفينة والاخرى كان يأتي الأولاد
join me and watch,
لينضموا الي في المراقبة
but their necks soon got sore, and they would go off to the boardwalk
لكن سرعان ماكانت تؤملهم أعناقهم ليذهبوا الى الممر الخشبي
to play video games and mingle with humans.
ليلعبوا ألعاب الفيديو ويختلطوا بالبشر
I was pretty good at the video games. I was not very good at the other part,
كنت بارعا بألعاب الفيديو ومريع بالاخرى
so I stayed alone with the cosmos.
لذا لطالما بقيت وحيدا مع نظام الكون
And that's when it happened.
وعندما حدث هذا
An elderly couple came walking down the street.
مر زوجان كبيران بالسن
I would say they were in their late seventies,
استطيع القول بأنها في أواخر السبعين
and I would say that they were on a date,
وأستطيع القول أيضا بأنهما كانا في موعد عاطفي
because he was wearing a very neat little suit
لأن الرجل كان يرتدي بدلة صغيرة أنيقة
with a yellow tie -- a brown suit.
بربطة عنق صفراء وبدلة بنية
And she was wearing a cardigan, because it was now fully night
بينما ارتدت هي سترة من الصوف بسبب برودة الجو ليلا
and a chill was coming in off the ocean.
كانت البرودة قادمة من المحيط
I remember, for some reason,
مازلت أذكر لسبب ما
that they were exactly the same height.
بأنهما كانا بالضبط بنفس الطول
And then they stopped, and the man turned to me
توقفا ليلتفت الرجل إلي
and said,
ويقول
"What are you looking for,
"مالذي تبحث عنه ؟
flying saucers?"
أطباق طائرة ؟"
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
You have to admit, that's a pretty boss piece of detective work
عليكم الاعتراف بأنه ضربة معلم في الاكتشاف
for an old man on a date.
بالنسبة لرجل كبير بالسن في موعد غرامي
But what was stranger still --
لكن الذي مازلت استغربه
and even I realized it at the time,
واستوعبته في وقته
as a nine-year-old child --
كطفل في التاسعة من عمره
was that they stopped at all.
بأنهما لم يتوقفا ابدا
That this old man would interrupt his moonlight stroll
وبأن رجل كبير بعمره سيقطع نزهته تحت ضوء القمر
with his sweetheart with the precise reason
مع حبيبة قلبه لسبب وجيه
of making fun of a child.
هو السخرية من طفل
"Oh," he said,
قال "آه؟
"little green men."
" الرجال الخضر الصغار "
And then his girlfriend joined in, too.
لتنضم اليه حبيبته فيما بعد
"There's no such thing as space men," she said.
لتقول " لايوجد مثل هذه الاشياء كرجال الفضاء "
"There's no such thing."
لايوجد مثل هذه الاشياء
And then they both laughed. "Ha, ha, ha."
ليضحكا فيما بعد سويا ها ها ها
I looked around.
نظرت حولي
The street was entirely empty.
كان الشارع مقفر من الناس
I had stopped hearing the sound of the ocean.
ولم اعد استطع سماع صوت المحيط
It was as though time had stopped.
اعتقدت لوهلة بأن الوقت توقف
I did not know why they were teasing me.
لم أفهم لما يحاولان إغاظتي
I looked into their strangely angry faces,
نظرت الى وجهيهما الغاضبين
and I remember wondering,
وأذكر بأني استغربت
are they wearing rubber masks?
هل يلبسان قناعين ؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
And what would be behind those rubber masks, if they were?
وماذا يوجد خلف هذان القناعين ان كانا حقا يرتدون قناعين؟
Giant, almond-shaped, unblinking eyes?
عيون لوزية لاترف ؟
Slits for mouths?
وشق على شكل فم ؟
The old man crooked his finger as though he were firing a gun,
فرقع المسن بأصابعه كمن يطلق النار من بندقيته
and then he made laser sounds.
ثم أطلق صوت ليزري
"Kew, kew, kew --
كيو كيو كيو
watch out."
"احترس "
And they turned at once and walked away.
ثم استدارا معا ورحلا
The old man reached out
مد المسن يده
his knobbly claw
يده التي على شكل مخلب
for the woman's hand,
ليد المرأة
and found it, and left me alone.
أمسكها وذهبا ليدعانني وحيدا
Now, you could describe this as a simple misunderstanding --
الان قد تصفون ماحدث كسوء فهم
a strange encounter among humans.
لقاء غير عادي في عالم البشر
Maybe it was swamp gas, but --
ربما هو مستنقع غاز لكن --
(Laughter) --
( ضحك )
I know what I saw.
انا متأكد مما رأيت
Close encounter two: Brookline, Massachusetts, 1984.
قريب من اللقاء الثاني : بروكلين , ماسشيتوس , 1984
I went to see the movie "Dune,"
حينها ذهبت لاشاهد فيلم "دون"
and a girl talked to me. Now, on its face --
أخذت فتاة تتحدث معي , الان وبصراحة
(Laughter) --
( ضحك )
this is impossible on its face, I realize --
هذا يعد من المستحيلات بصراحة أدركت
but it is absolutely true.
لكنه صحيح كليا
It was opening night, naturally.
انت ليلة في الهواء الطلق , طبيعية
I went with my friend Tim McGonigal, who sat on my left.
ذهبت مع صديقي تيم مكغونيغال الذي جلس على شمالي
On my right was the girl in question.
وعلى يميني الفتاة المشبوهة
She had long, curly black hair, a blue jean jacket.
كان شعرها مجعد طويل اسود ترتدي جاكيت جينز ازرق
I remember, she had some sort of injury to her ankle,
مازلت أذكر , كان كاحلها مصابا نوعا ما
an Ace bandage, and she had crutches.
ضمادة آس وعكازات
She was very tall, I would say.
استطيع القول بأنها كانت طويلة جدا
I was starting high school at the time. I would say she was a junior,
كنت قد بدأت المرحلة الثانوية وأستطيع القول أنها كانت أصغر
but I had never seen her before. She didn't go to my school.
لم أكن قد رأيتها من قبل فهي لم تقصد مدرستنا
I didn't know her name, and I never will.
لم أعرف اسمها ولم يكن في نيتي أن أعرف
She was sitting with someone who I presume was her mother,
كانت تجلس مع من افترضت بأنها أمها
and they were talking about the novel, "Dune."
وكانتا تتحدثان عن رواية دون
They were both big fans, mother and daughter --
كانتا من كبار المعجبات الام وابنتها --
very unusual.
على غير العادة
They were talking about how their favorite characters
كانت تتحدثان عن شخصيتهما المفضلتين
were the giant sandworms.
كانتا دودتي كتب عملاقتين
And then it got stranger.
ثم أصبحتا غريبتين
That's when she turned to me and said,
حينها التفت الي وقالت
"Are you looking forward to seeing the movie?"
" هل تنتظر رؤية الفيلم " ؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
First of all, I was embarrassed
في البدء شعرت بالحرج
because I had not read the novel "Dune" at that time.
لأنني لم أكن قد قرأت رواية دون في ذلك الوقت
I was merely a connoisseur of movies
لم أكن ذو خبرة في الافلام
featuring desert planets, as I still am.
كنبتة صحراوية , ومازلت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it was also the tone of how she asked the question:
لكن طريقتها في كيفية طرح السؤال
apropos of nothing, like she didn't even care about the answer,
لاتحمل في طياتها شيء وكأنها لاتهتم لجوابي
as though she just wanted to talk to me.
كل ماتريده كان الحديث الي
I did not know what to say. I said, "Yes."
لم أعرف ماذا أقول أكتفيت بقول "نعم"
I did not even turn my head.
حتى أنني لم أحرك رأسي
The movie began.
بدأ الفيلم
I need not remind you that this was David Lynch's version of "Dune,"
ولا تحتاجون لتذكيركم بأنه نسخة دافيد لينشز من "دون"
in which all of the characters
بكل شخصياتها
were sexy and deformed at the same time.
الجذابة والبغيضة في آن واحد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There was a character called the Third-Stage Guild Navigator,
كان هناك شخصية تدعى المستكشف من الطبقة الثالثة
which was a kind of giant, floating fetus-creature
الذي كان عبارة عن جنين عائم عملاق
that lived in a giant tank with this orange mist
الذي يعيش بتنكة عملاقة ذات غشاء برتقالي
of psychedelic spice
من التوابل المخدرة
swirling around him,
تحوم حوله
allowing him to bend space and time.
سامحة له بتبديد التوابل والوقت
He could never leave the tank
هو لا يستطيع أن يترك علبته
or interact with the outside world.
او التأقلم مع المحيط الخارجي
He had become, in his isolation,
أصبح في منفاه
so deformed and so sexy,
غريب جدا وجذاب جدا
that he had to talk through a kind of old-timey radio
حيث تسنت له الفرصة في زمن مضى للحديث بالراديو
to the outside world, and could never touch them.
للعالم الخارجي حيث لا يستطيعون أن يلمسوه
I mean, I liked him a lot better than the sandworms.
أعني بأنني أحببته أكثر بكثير من دودتي الكتب
The sandworms were fine, but your favorite character?
دودتا الكتب كانتا جيدتين لكن ماهي شخصيتك المفضلة ؟
Please.
ارجوكم
When the movie ended,
عندما انتهى الفيلم
everyone seemed very happy
بدا الجميع سعداء
to get up and get out of the theatre as soon as possible.
للنهوض والخروج فورا من القاعة
Except for the girl.
عدا الفتاة
As I walked out, her pace slowed.
عندما هممت للخروج رأيت خطواتها تتباطئ
Perhaps it was the crutches,
ربما بسبب العكازات
but it seemed --
لكن يبدو --
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
it seemed as though she might want to talk to me again.
لكن يبدو أنها تريد الحديث معي مجددا
When I say it out loud, it sounds so ridiculous,
عندما حادثتها بالخارج بصوت عال , بدا المشهد مضحك جدا
but I can only come to the conclusion
لكني أستطيع فقط الوصول للخلاصة بأن
that it was what, in the alien abductee community,
هذا ماكان يسميه مجتمع المخلوقات الفضائية الغريبة
they call a "screen memory":
كانوا يسمونها ب " شاشة الذاكرة "
a ridiculous false recollection designed by their brain
أخطاء مضحكة مصممة بعقولهم
to cover up some trauma -- say, of being kidnapped
لتغطية الصدمات -- لنقول اختطافهم
and flown off to a sex pyramid.
ليطيروا ليمارسوا بعدها الجنس في الاهرام
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so I sure am glad
وأنا متأكد من سروري
I did not slow down to talk to her.
لذا لم أبطئ لأتحدث معها
I sure am glad I never saw her again.
وأنا أكيد بأنني لم أرها من جديد
Close encounter three: Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
اللقاء القريب الثالث : ف يلادلفيا . بنسلفينيا
In the mid-to-late '80s,
في نهاية الثمانينات
the novelist Whitley Strieber wrote a book called "Communion,"
كتب الروائي وايتلي ستريبر كتاب يسمى " الطائفة"
in which he described his own lifelong experiences
حيث يصف تجاربه الحياتية
being abducted by aliens.
واختطافه على يد المخلوقات الفضائية
And he also described the phenomenon known in this community
ووصف أيضا ظواهر معروفة في هذا المجتمع
as "lost time,"
كـ "الوقت الضائع "
where Whitley Strieber would suddenly become aware
حيث ادرك فجأة ويتلي ستربر
that he could not remember the previous ten minutes,
أنه لايستطيع تذكر ماحدث قبل عشر دقائق
or the previous ten hours, or the previous ten days.
او ماحدث قبل عشر ساعات , او ماحدث قبل عشر ايام
And would come to the conclusion that that was when the aliens
حيث أستنتج استنتاج مفاده أن المخلوقات الفضائية
were taking him and giving him rectal probes.
اختطفته وأعطته حقنه شرجية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This book became, naturally, an enormous best-seller.
أصبح هذا الكتاب تلقائيا من الكتب الاكثر مبيعا
This image by Ted Joseph was from that book,
هذه الصورة المرسومة بيد تيد جوزيف مأخوذة من هذا الكتاب
and was his, sort of, police sketch
وكانت نوعا ما رسم بوليسي
of what the creatures looked like
عن كيف تبدو هذه المخلوقات
that Whitley Strieber had described to him.
ذلك أن ويتلي ستربر وصفهم له
And it was so successful that they made it into a movie.
ونجح في أن يخرج من صورهم فيلما
And in 1989, the way I remember it,
في عام 1989 الطريقة التي اذكرها
I was in Philadelphia
كنت في فيلادلفيا مع
visiting my girlfriend, and we decided,
ازور صديقتي وقررنا
apropos of nothing, to go see this movie.
من دون قصد أن نذهب لرؤية هذا الفيلم
And the way I remember it, the movie featured these details.
مازلت أذكر تلك التفاصيل الدقيقة في الفيلم
One: Whitley Strieber
الاول : ويتلي ستربر
was played by Christopher Walken.
لعب دوره كريستوفر والكين
Two: the alien was played by a rubber puppet.
الثاني: المخلوقات الفضائية لعب دورها لصوص الالعاب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Three: there was a surprisingly long
الثالث : كان هناك تسلسل طويل مفاجئ
sequence of the film in which the rubber puppet
من الفيلم حيث يعطي لصوص الالعاب
gives Christopher Walken a rectal probe.
كريستوفر والكين حقنة شرجية
Four: this was being shown
الرابع : كان هناك عرض
in a regular movie theater in Center City, Philadelphia.
لفيلم عادي في قاعة وسط فيلادلفيا
Five: all of which is to say,
الخامس : الجميع قال
they made a movie out of the book, "Communion,"
بأن هناك فيلم مبني على كتاب " الطائفة"
and it starred Christopher Walken.
بطولة المتألق كريستوفر والكين
Does something seem strange about this to you?
هل يبدو شيء مما قلته مستغرب لكم ؟
Something odd? Something off? Something wrong with this picture?
غير طبيعي ؟ شاذ ؟ أهناك شيء خاطئ في هذه الصورة التي ذكرتها؟
Think about it. Yes. The answer is:
فكروا بهذا . اجل الجواب هو
I had a girlfriend. What?
كان لدي صديقة . ماذا ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How did this happen? When did this happen?
كيف حدث هذا ؟ متى حدث هذا ؟
I remember walking out of the theater
أذكر بأني كنت اسير خارج القاعة
and becoming suddenly aware of this fact,
وأدركت فجأة لتلك الحقيقة
as we walked hand in hand,
بينما كنا نمشي يد بيد
and pondering these very same questions.
ونتسائل ذات السؤال
And to this day, I have no answer for you.
وحتى يومنا هذا لا أملك جوابا لكم
Close encounter four: the Algarve,
اللقاء القريب الرابع : الغارف
Portugal, 1991.
البرتغال,1991
Some years later, I and this woman --
بضع سنوات بعدها , انا وذات المرأة --
we'll call her "Catherine Fletcher" --
لندعوها بـ " كاثرين فليتشر " --
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
went traveling through the south of Portugal together.
سافرنا سويا باتجاه جنوب البرتغال
We stayed in old, crumbling, walled cities,
أقمنا في مدينة مسورة قديمة متداعية
in tiny little hotels,
في فندق صغير
and we would climb up to the roof and drink Vinho Verde
وكان علينا التسلق الى العلية لنشرب فينهو فيردي
and watch the sun set and play checkers.
ومشاهدة غروب الشمس ولعب الداما
What? Did we do this? Really? Does anyone do this?
ماذا؟ هل قمتم بذلك ؟ حقا ؟ أقام أحدكم بهذا ؟
We went to some topless beaches.
ذهبنا الى شواطئ التعري
Excuse me? No, not in my life.
عفوا ؟ لا ليس في حياتي
For what it's worth, we went to Sagres,
ماهو أسوأ . ذهبنا الى ساغريس
which was considered, at the time, to be the end of the world.
حيث كانت تعتبر في ذاك الوقت نهاية العالم
And there I was chased by a pack of feral dogs on the dock,
وكنت مطاردا من قبل مجموعة من الكلاب الضالة
and the lead dog bit me on the ass,
وعضني أحدهم في مؤخرتي
requiring me to go to a strange Portuguese clinic
حيث اضطررت الى الذهاب عيادة برتغالية غريبة
and receive an ass shot.
لأخذ بعدها حقنة في المؤخرة
Make of that what you will.
اسموها ماتشائون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Our last day in Portugal,
اخر يوم لنا في البرتغال
we were in the district capital of Faro,
كنا في عاصمة مقاطعة الفارو
and Catherine decided that she wanted to go to the beach
وكانت كاثرين قد قررت ان تذهب الى الشاطئ
one last time.
للمرة الاولى والاخيرة
Now, Faro is a bustling little city,
الان الفارو مدينة صاخبة صغيرة
and to get to the beach, she explained, you would have to take
وللذهاب الى الشاطئ , أوضحت كاثرين لي , عليك أن تأخذ
a bus and then a boat.
حافلة ثم قارب لتصل الى هناك
And did I want to come with?
هل علي الذهاب معها ؟
But I was exhausted and dog-bitten, and so I said, "No."
لكنني كنت متعب ومعضوض من كلب لذا قلت لا
I remember what she looked like before she left.
أذكر كيف كانت تبدو قبل أن تذهب
The freckles had grown
كانت الغرابة تكبر
and multiplied on her face and shoulders,
وكانت أضعاف مضاعفة في وجهها وأكتافها
clustering into a kind of a tan.
متحولة الى نوع من الاصباغ
A tan, we were both tan --
أصباغ , كنا كلانا مصبوغين
is this true?
هل هذا صحيح ؟
Her eyes were extra bright and extra blue, as a result.
عيناها كانتا مزرقتان بلمعان أكثر , كنتيجة لرفضي
She was smiling.
وكانت تبتسم
She was a single woman about to go alone into a country,
كانت انثى عزباء تنوي الذهاب الى الريف بمفردها
not even speaking the language,
لاتتحدث حتى لغتهم
to travel alone by bus and boat
لتسافر وحيدة بالحافلة ثم بقارب
to go to a beach she did not know
متجهة الى شاطيء لاتعرفه
or had never seen.
ولا حتى رأته
I loved her, and then she went out
أحبتتها , ثم ذهبت
into that strange, alien land.
لأرض غريبة بعيدة
It took me some time to come to my senses.
احتجت الى بعض الوقت لاعود الى رشدي
I had my own "lost time" moment,
لقد أصبح لدي "وقتي الضائع "
where I woke up and suddenly realized
حيث استيقظت لافهم
it was very late in the day, almost dinnertime,
كان الوقت متأخرا تقريبا , تقريبا وقت الغداء
and she had not come back.
ولم تكن قد عادت بعد
Nervous, I went down to the street to look for her.
شعرت بالقلق فاتجهت الى الشارع بحثا عنها
Now, I did not speak Portuguese.
وانا لا اتحدث البرتغالية
I did not know where the beach was.
ولا أعرف طريق الشاطئ
I could not call her on a cell phone because this was 1991,
ولا استطيع طلبها عن طريق هاتفها النقال لأننا كنا في 1991
and the aliens had not given us that technology yet.
ولم تعطنا المخلوقات الفضائية تلك التقنية بعد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I realized that the day would only have
حينها أدركت ان اليوم سيحمل في جعبته
two possible outcomes:
احتمالين لاثالث لهما
either Catherine would come back to the hotel,
اما ان تعود كاثرين الى الفندق
or she would never come back to the hotel.
او أنها لن تعود أبدا
And so I sat down to wait.
وهكذا لم يكن بيدي الا الانتظار
I did not watch the skies, but the very end of the street
لم أكن اراقب السماء فقط كانت عيناني معلقتان على نهاية الشارع
where the buses and cars and pedestrians
حيث الحافلات والسيارات والمشاة
and little scooters were moving along.
لم يكن هناك سوى القليل من الدراجات تسير على طول الخط
And I watched those constellations shift,
كنت اراقب تحركهم في مجموعات
hoping that they would part and I would see her face.
أمل أن يتفرقوا وأن أستطيع رؤية وجهها
It was at that moment,
في تلك اللحظة
in that very small town of 30,000 or so,
في مدينة صغيرة جدا يبلغ تعداد سكانها 300 الف تقريبا
that I truly appreciated the vastness of the universe
حيث قدرت حقا ضخامة الكون
and the searching we might do in it.
وكمية البحث التي سنقوم بها
And that's when the Liberians came along.
في تلك اللحظة حيث ظهر اللايبيريون
Five young men -- all laughing, happy, traveling together,
خمس شباب -- يضحكون . فرحين , يسافرون مع بعضهم البعض
coming back to this hotel where they were staying.
عادوا أدراجهم الى هذا الفندق حيث يقيمون
One of them was named Joseph, and he asked me
أحدهم كان يدعى جوزيف قام بسؤالي
what was I doing, and I explained.
ماذا أفعل وقمت بشرح قصتي له
And he said, "Don't worry." He was sure that Catherine would be safe.
حينها اخبرني بأن لا أقلق فكاثرين لابد أن تكون بخير
But he did not seem so very sure,
لكنه لم يبدوا واثقا جدا
for he sat down to wait with me.
حيث أنه بقي لينتظرها معي
And for the next two hours, they all waited with me:
وفي الساعتين التي تلتها كان الجميع ينتظرون معي
taking turns, going up to their room, coming back,
يتبادلون الادوار , يصعدون الى غرفهم ويعودون
telling me jokes, distracting me.
يقصون النكت عليي , يحاولون الهائي
Two hours, they gave me a message.
ساعتين , ليوصلون لي رسالة مفادها
We are not alone.
بأننا لسنا وحدنا
And then, in the middle of a sentence, at the very birth of twilight,
ثم بداية الغروب
I turned and looked down the street.
نهضت لأنظر الى الشارع
The stars aligned, and she came back.
ظهرت النجوم . وعادت كاثرين أخيرا
She was smiling. She did not understand why I was so worried.
كانت تبتسم ولم تفهم سببا لقلقي
Neither did the Liberians,
ولا اللايبيريين حتى
although there was a huge amount of relief in their laughter
على الرغم من وجود الكثير من الارتياح في ضحكاتهم
as they clapped us on the back, and went back up to their room
وكأن حمل من على ظهورهم سقط ليذهبوا الى غرفتهم بعد ذلك
and left us alone in the street, holding hands.
ويتركوننا لوحدنا في الشارع متعانقي الايدي
An event like this leaves a scar on the memory,
في مناسبات كهذه يصبح الندب من الماضي
much like a piece of alien technology
كقطعة من تكنلوجيا المخلوقات الفضائية
that has been inserted into your buttocks
التي تم ادراجها في أردافكم
by a "Portuguese doctor."
بيد دكتور برتغالي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And even now, a decade and a half later,
حتى الان , عقد ونصف مضى
even now that we are married,
الى الان ونحن متزوجان
I look for her still, whenever she is not in the room.
الى الان ابحث عنها في كل مكان ان لم اجدها في الغرفة
And even though, I think you'll agree, it is probable
على الرغم من ذلك , وأعتقد بأنكم ستوافقونني , انه ربما
that during the time she was away,
في الوقت الذي كانت به بعيدة
she was kidnapped and replaced by an alien clone,
ربما اختطفت وبدلت بمخلوق فضائي مستنسخ
I love her and wait for her still.
مازلت أحبها وأنتظرها
Thank you for your kind attention.
أشكر لكم لطفكم واستماعكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)